One of the problems of writing, and working, and looking at the Internet
أحد مشاكل الكتابة والعمل والنظر في الإنترنت
is that it's very hard to separate fashion from deep change.
هي أنه من الصعب الفصل ما بين الموضة والتغيير الجذري.
And so, to start helping that, I want to take us back to 1835.
ولبداية مساعدة ذلك، أريد أن أنتقل بكم إلى عام 1835.
In 1835, James Gordon Bennett founded the first mass-circulation newspaper
عام 1835، أسس جيمس غوردون بيننت أول صحيفة واسعة الإنتشار
in New York City.
في مدينة نيويورك.
And it cost about 500 dollars to start it,
ولقد كلّفت حوالي 500 دولاراً لبدايتها،
which was about the equivalent of 10,000 dollars of today.
التي كانت تعادل حوالي 10،000 دولاراً اليوم.
By 15 years later, by 1850, doing the same thing
بعد 15 لاحقاً، بحلول عام 1850، فعل نفس الشئ
-- starting what was experienced as a mass--circulation daily paper
- بداية ما عُرف كصحيفة يومية واسعة الإنتشار
-- would come to cost two and a half million dollars.
-- سيكلف حوالي مليوني ونصف دولار.
10,000, two and a half million, 15 years.
10،000، إلى مليوني ونصف، في 15 عاماً.
That's the critical change that is being inverted by the Net.
هذا هو التغيير الجذري الذي قلبته الشبكة.
And that's what I want to talk about today,
وذلك ما ارغب بالحديث عنه اليوم،
and how that relates to the emergence of social production.
وكيف أن ذلك يرتبط بنشوء الإنتاج الإجتماعي.
Starting with newspapers, what we saw was high cost as an initial requirement
بداية من الصحف، ما شهدناه هو كلفة عالية كمتطلب مبدئي
for making information, knowledge and culture, which led to a stark bifurcation
لصنع المعلومات، المعرفة والثقافة، الذي قاد إلى تشعب صارخ
between producers -- who had to be able to raise financial capital,
بين المنتجين-- الذين توجب عليهم المقدرة على توفير رؤوس الأموال،
just like any other industrial organization --
تماماً مثل أي مؤسسة صناعية أخرى --
and passive consumers that could choose from a certain set of
والمستهلك السلبي الذي يمكنه الإختيار من مجموعة محددة
things that this industrial model could produce.
من الأشياء التي يمكن أن يوفرها النموذج الصناعي.
Now, the term "information society," "information economy,"
الآن، مصطلح " مجتمع المعلومات،" " إقتصاد المعلومات،"
for a very long time has been used as the thing that comes after
لفترة طويلة كان يستخدم كشئ يأتي لاحقاً
the industrial revolution. But in fact, for purposes of understanding what's happening
بعد الثورة الصناعية. لكن في الواقع، لأهداف فهم ما يجري
today, that's wrong. Because for 150 years, we've had an information economy.
اليوم، فأن ذلك خطأ. لأنه طوال 150 عاماً، كان لدينا إقتصاد معلومات.
It's just been industrial,
فقط للتو أصبح صناعياً .
which means those who were producing had to have a way of raising money
الذي يعني أن أولئك الذين كانوا ينتجون توجب عليهم توفير طريقة لجني المال
to pay those two and a half million dollars, and later, more for the telegraph,
ليدفعوا تلك المليونين ونصف دولار، ولاحقاً، المزيد للتلغراف،
and the radio transmitter, and the television, and eventually the mainframe.
والنقل على المذياع، والتلفاز، وفي نهاية المطاف الكمبيوتر الضخم (mainframe).
And that meant they were market based, or they were government owned,
وذلك يعني انها كانت تعتمد على السوق، أو أنها مملوكة للدولة،
depending on what kind of system they were in. And this characterized and anchored
إعتماداً على أي نوع من الأنظمة كانت فيها. ويتميز هذا ويرتكز
the way information and knowledge were produced for the next 150 years.
على الطريقة التي أُنتجت بها المعلومات والمعرفة خلال ال 150 سنة التالية.
Now, let me tell you a different story. Around June 2002,
الآن، دعوني أخبركم بقصة مختلفة. حوالي يونيو 2002،
the world of supercomputers had a bombshell.
تلقى عام الحواسيب الضخمة قنبلة.
The Japanese had, for the first time, created the fastest supercomputer --
صنع اليابانيون لأول مرة أسرع حاسوب ضخم --
the NEC Earth Simulator -- taking the primary from the U.S.,
محاكي الأرض لشركة NEC -- آخذين المبادرة من الولايات المتحدة،
and about two years later -- this, by the way, is measuring the trillion floating-point
وبعد قرابة العامين-- هذا، بالمناسبة، يقاس بتريلليون عملية نقطة عائمة
operations per second that the computer's capable of running --
في الثانية التي يستطيع الحاسوب القيام بها.
sigh of relief: IBM [Blue Gene] has just edged ahead of the NEC Earth Simulator.
تنفس الصعداء: حاسوب جين بلو لشركة IBM قد تخطى للتو محاكي الأرض لشركة NEC .
All of this completely ignores the fact that throughout this period,
كل هذا يتجاهل كلياً حقيقة أنه خلال هذه الفترة،
there's another supercomputer running in the world -- SETI@home.
كان هناك حاسوب ضخم آخر يعمل في العالم-- SETI@Home
Four and a half million users around the world, contributing their
-- أربعة ونصف مليون مستخدم حول العالم، يساهمون
leftover computer cycles, whenever their computer isn't working,
بما تبقى من دورات حواسيبهم، في أي وقت لا تعمل حواسيبهم،
by running a screen saver, and together sharing their resources to create
بتشغيل حافظة الشاشة، ويتقاسمون سوياً الموارد لتكوين
a massive supercomputer that NASA harnesses to analyze the data
حاسوب ضخم هائل تستخدمه وكالة ناسا لتحليل البيانات
coming from radio telescopes.
الواردة من التلسكوبات اللاسلكية.
What this picture suggests to us is that we've got a radical change in the way
ما تقترحه هذه الصورة لنا هو أننا حصلنا على تغيير جذري في طريقة
information production and exchange is capitalized. Not that it's become
إنتاج المعلومات وأن التبادل قد تم إستثماره. لا أنه أصبح
less capital intensive -- that there's less money that's required
أقل كثافة في رأس المال -- بحيث هناك أموال أقل مطلوبة
-- but that the ownership of this capital, the way the capitalization happens,
-- بل أن ملكية رأس المال هذا، الطريقة التي يحدث بها الإستثمار،
is radically distributed. Each of us, in these advanced economies,
هي موزعة جذرياً. كلٌ منّا، في هذه الإقتصاديات المتقدمة،
has one of these, or something rather like it -- a computer.
لديه أحد من هذه، ، أو بالأحرى شيء مثل ذلك -- حاسوب.
They're not radically different from routers inside the middle of the network.
إنها ليست مختلفة جذرياً من المسارات في منتصف الشبكة.
And computation, storage and communications capacity are in the hands of
والحسابات، التخزين وسعة الإتصالات التي في متناول
practically every connected person -- and these are the basic physical
كل شخص متصل عمليا-- وهذه هي أساسيات
capital means necessary for producing information, knowledge and culture,
وسائل رأس المال المادي الضرورية لإنتاج المعلومات، المعرفة والثقافة،
in the hands of something like 600 million to a billion people around the planet.
بين أيدي شئ مثل 600 مليون إلى مليار شخص حول كوكب الأرض.
What this means is that for the first time since the industrial revolution,
ما يعنيه هذا هو أنه للمرة الأولى منذ الثورة الصناعية،
the most important means, the most important components of the core
أكثر الوسائل أهمية -- أكثر العناصر أهمية لعصب
economic activities -- remember, we are in an information economy
الأنشطة الإقتصادية -- تذكروا، نحن في إقتصاد المعلومات
-- of the most advanced economies, and there more than anywhere else,
-- لأكثر الإقتصاديات تقدماً، وهناك أكثر من أي مكان آخر ،
are in the hands of the population at large. This is completely different than what we've
متاحة في أيدي جميع الناس. هذا مختلف كلياً من كل
seen since the industrial revolution. So we've got communications and computation
ما شهدناه منذ الثورة الصناعية. إذاً فقد حصلنا على إتصالات ومقدرة
capacity in the hands of the entire population,
حسابية في أيدي كل البشرية،
and we've got human creativity, human wisdom, human experience
وحصلنا على إبداعية البشر، حكمة البشر، خبرة البشر
-- the other major experience, the other major input --
-- والتجربة الرئيسية الأخرى، والمدخلات الرئيسية الأخرى.
which unlike simple labor -- stand here turning this lever all day long --
التي تختلف عن العمالة البسيطة -- قف هنا حوّل هذا الذراع طوال اليوم --
is not something that's the same or fungible among people.
إنه ليس الشيئ نفسه أو مثيله بين الناس.
Any one of you who has taken someone else's job, or tried to give yours
ليس أي شخص منكم أخذ قد أخذ عمل شخص آخر أو حاول إعطاء
to someone else, no matter how detailed the manual, you cannot transmit
عمله لشخص آخر، مهما كان الدليل مفصلاً، لا يمكنك إرسال
what you know, what you will intuit under a certain set of circumstances.
ما تعرفه، ، ما ستشعر به في إطار مجموعة معينة من الظروف.
In that we're unique, and each of us holds this critical input
نحن في ذلك متفردون، وكلٌ منّا يحمل هذه المدخلات الحرجة
into production as we hold this machine.
داخل الإنتاج بينما نمسك هذه الآلة.
What's the effect of this? So, the story that most people know
ما هو تأثير هذا؟ إذاً فالقصة التي يعلمها معظم الناس
is the story of free or open source software.
هي قصة البرمجيات المجانية أو ذات المصدر المفتوح.
This is market share of Apache Web server
هذه هي حصة السوق لخادم ويب أباتشي
-- one of the critical applications in Web-based communications.
-- أحد التطبيقات الهامة في الإتصالات القائمة على الويب.
In 1995, two groups of people said,
عام 1995، قالت مجموعتان من الناس،
"Wow, this is really important, the Web! We need a much better Web server!"
"واو، هذا مهم حقاً، الويب! نحتاج لخادم ويب أفضل بكثير!"
One was a motley collection of volunteers who just decided,
أحدهم كانت مجموعة متنافرة من المتطوعين الذين قرروا فقط،
you know, we really need this, we should write one,
كما تعلمون، نحن نحتاج هذا حقاً، يجب أن نبرمج أحدها،
and what are we going to do with what --
وما سنفعله بما --
well, we're gonna share it! And other people will be able to develop it.
حسناً، سنقوم بتقاسمه! وسيستطيع بقية الناس تطويره.
The other was Microsoft.
والمجموعة الأخرى كانت شركة مايكروسوفت.
Now, if I told you that 10 years later, the motley crew of people, who didn't control
الآن، إذا أخبرتكم قبل 10 سنوات، أن المجموعة المتنافرة من الناس الذين لم يتحكموا
anything that they produced, acquired 20 percent of the market
في أي شئ قد حازوا على حصة 20 بالمائة من السوق
and was the red line, it would be amazing! Right?
وكانت الخط الاحمر، فسيكون مذهلاً! صحيح؟
Think of it in minivans. A group of automobile
فكروا بالأمر في السيارات الميني. مجموعة من مهندسي
engineers on their weekends are competing with Toyota. Right?
السيارات في عطلة نهاية أسبوعهم كانوا ينافسون شركة تايوتا. صحيح؟
But, in fact, of course, the story is it's the 70 percent,
لكن في الواقع، القصة ليست عن ال 70 بالمائة،
including the major e-commerce site -- 70 percent of a critical application
تشمل مواقع التجارة الإلكترونية الكبيرة-- 70 بالمائة من التطبيقات المهمة
on which Web-based communications and applications work is produced in this form, in
التي فيها تنتج الإتصالات المبنية على الويب وعمل التطبيقات في هذا الشكل
direct competition with Microsoft. Not in a side issue --
في منافسة مباشرة مع مايكروسوفت، ليس في قضية هامشية
in a central strategic decision to try to capture a component of the Net.
-- في قرار مركزي إستراتيجي لمحاولة التحكم في عنصر على الشبكة.
Software has done this in a way that's been very visible, because
أنجزت البرمجيات هذا بطريقة كانت واضحة، لأنها
it's measurable. But the thing to see is that this actually happens throughout the Web.
قابلة للقياس. لكن الشئ الملاحظ أن هذا في الواقع يحدث عبر الويب
So, NASA, at some point, did an experiment where they took images of Mars
بحيث أن ناسا، في نقطة ما، قامت بتجربة حيث أخذوا صوراً لكوكب المريخ
that they were mapping, and they said, instead of having three or four
الذي كانوا يخططونه . وقد قالوا بدلا عن توظيف ثلاثة إلى أربعة
fully trained Ph.D.s doing this all the time, let's break it up into small components,
حملة دكتوراة مدربين لفعل هذا طوال الوقت، لنقوم بتجزئتها لأجزاء أصغر،
put it up on the Web, and see if people, using a very simple interface,
ونضعها على الويب، ونرى إن كان الناس، بإستخدام واجهات بسيطة للغاية،
will actually spend five minutes here,
سيقضون خمس دقائق هنا،
10 minutes there, clicking. After six months,
10 دقائق هناك، ينقرون. بعد ستة أشهر،
85,000 people used this to generate mapping at a
كان 85،000 شخص قد استخدموها لتخطيط
faster rate than the images were coming in, which was, quote,
بمعدل أسرع من الصور الواردة، التي كانت، إقتباس،
"practically indistinguishable from the markings of a fully-trained Ph.D.,"
" عملياً لا يمكن تفريقها من ترسيم حامل الدكتوراة المدرب بالكامل،"
once you showed it to a number of people and computed the average.
بمجرد أن قمت بعرضها على الناس وحسبت المتوسط.
Now, if you have a little girl, and she goes and writes to
الآن إن كان لديك فتاة صغيرة، وهي تذهب وتكتب إلى
-- well, not so little, medium little -- tries to do research on Barbie.
-- حسناً، ليست صغيرة جداً، متوسطة الصغر-- تحاول البحث عن دمية باربي.
And she'll come to Encarta, one of the main online encyclopedias.
وستصل إلى موسوعة إنكارتا، أحد الموسوعات الرئيسية على الإنترنت،
This is what you'll find out about Barbie. This is it, there's nothing more to the definition,
فهذا ما ستجده عن باربي. هذا هو، ليس هناك أكثر من التعريف،
including, "manufacturers" -- plural -- "now more commonly produce
ويشمل المصنعين "-- بصيغة الجمع-- "الأكثر شيوعاً حالياً
ethnically diverse dolls, like this black Barbie." Which is vastly better
دمى متنوعة عرقيا ، مثل هذه الباربي السوداء." التي هي أفضل بكثير
than what you'll find in the encyclopedia.com,
مما سنجده في موقع encyclopedia.com/
which is Barbie, Klaus. (Laughter)
التي هي باربي، كلاوس. (ضحك)
On the other hand, if they go to Wikipedia, they'll find a genuine article
على الجانب الآخر، إذا ذهبت إلى ويكي بيديا، فأنها ستجد موضوعاً فريداً من النوع
-- and I won't talk a lot about Wikipedia, because Jimmy Wales is here --
-- ولن أتحدث عن ويكي بيديا، لأن جيمي ويلز"مؤسسها" هنا --
but roughly equivalent to what you would find in the Britannica, differently written,
ولكن ما يعادل تقريبا ما ستجده في بريتانيكا، مكتوب بصورة مختلفة،
including the controversies over body image and commercialization,
وضمنها جدل حول صورة الجسد والتسويق،
the claims about the way in which she's a good role model, etc.
والادعاءات حول الطريقة التي انها قدوة طيبة ، وهلم جرا.
Another portion is not only how content is produced, but how relevance is produced.
جزء آخر هو ليس فقط كيف تنتج المحتويات، لكن كم هي ذات صلة.
The claim to fame of Yahoo! was, we hire people to look -- originally, not anymore
إدعاء الشهرة بالنسبة لياهو! كان، أننا نوظّف أناس للبحث -- في الأصل، ليس بعد الآن
-- we hire people to look at websites and tell you --
-- نحن نوظّف أناس ليبحثوا عن مواقع ويخبروكم --
if they're in the index, they're good. This, on the other hand, is what 60,000
إن كانت في الفهرس، فهي جيدة. هذا على الجانب الآخر، هو ما ينتجه
passionate volunteers produce in the Open Directory Project,
60،000 متطوع شغوفين في مشروع الفهرس المفتوح.
each one willing to spend an hour or two on something they really care about,
يرغب كل منهم بقضاء ساعة أو ساعتين على شئ يهتم به حقاً،
to say, this is good. So, this is the Open Directory Project, with 60,000 volunteers,
ليقول، هذا جيد. لذا فمشروع الفهرس المفتوح هذا، ب 60،000 متطوع،
each one spending a little bit of time, as opposed to a few hundred
يقضي كل مهم القليل من الوقت، كنقيض لعدة مئات
fully paid employees. No one owns it, no one owns the output,
من الموظفين المدفوع لهم بالكامل. لا أحد يملكه، لا أحد يملك المخرجات،
it's free for anyone to use and it's the output of people acting out of social
إنه مجاني الإستخدام للجميع وهي مخرجات لناس يعملون بدوافع إجتماعية
and psychological motivations to do something interesting.
ونفسية لفعل شئ مثير.
This is not only outside of businesses. When you think of what is the critical innovation
هذا ليس فقط خارج الأعمال. حينما نفكر بماهية الإبتكار المهم
of Google, the critical innovation is outsourcing the one most important thing --
لشركة غوغل، فأن الإبتكار المهم هو الإستعانة بمصادر خارجية لأحد أهم الأشياء--
the decision about what's relevant -- to the community of the Web as a whole,
القرار حول الشئ ذا الصلة -- لمجتمع الويب ككل،
doing whatever they want to do: so, page rank.
والقيام بكل ما تريد القيام به. لذا -- رتبة الصفحة.
The critical innovation here is instead of our engineers, or our people saying
الإبتكار الحرج هنا هو عوضاً عن أن يقول مهندسينا أو مجموعتنا
which is the most relevant, we're going to go out and count what you,
أي شئ هو الأكثر صلة، سنذهب حول الويب ونحسب
people out there on the Web, for whatever reason -- vanity, pleasure --
لكم أنتم على الشبكة، لأي سبب كان -- الغرور، المتعة--
produced links, and tied to each other. We're going to count those, and count them up.
الوصلات المنتجة، ونربطها ببعضها البعض. سنقوم بحسابها، ونرتبها تصاعدياً.
And again, here, you see Barbie.com, but also, very quickly,
ومجدداً، هنا، تشاهدون Barbie.com، لكن أيضاً بسرعة جداً،
Adiosbarbie.com, the body image for every size. A contested cultural object,
Adiosbarbie.com، صورة الجسد لكل حجم. كائن ثقافي متنازع عليه،
which you won't find anywhere soon on Overture, which is the classic
الذي لن تجده في أي مكان عرض قريباً، التي هي آليات
market-based mechanism: whoever pays the most is highest on the list.
السوق التقليدية. من يدفع أكثر سيكون أعلى القائمة.
So, all of that is in the creation of content, of relevance, basic human expression.
إذاً فكل ذلك في إنشاء المحتوى ، ذا الصلة، تعبيرات بشرية أساسية.
But remember, the computers were also physical. Just physical materials
لكن تذكروا، كانت الكمبيوترات كذلك فيزيائية. مجرد مواد فيزيائية
-- our PCs -- we share them together. We also see this in wireless.
-- حواسيبنا، نحن نتقاسمها معاً. نحن أيضاً نرى هذا في الشبكة اللاسلكية.
It used to be wireless was one person owned the license, they transmitted in an
في العادة في الشبكة اللاسلكية شخص واحد يمتلك الرخصة، وينقل
area, and it had to be decided whether they would be licensed or based on property.
في مساحة، ويجب التقرير سواء سيتم ترخيصها أم بناء على اساس الملكية.
What we're seeing now is that computers and radios are becoming so sophisticated
ما نشهده الآن هو أن الكمبيوترات والراديوهات تصبح أكثر تطوراً
that we're developing algorithms to let people own machines, like Wi-Fi devices,
بحيث نقوم بتطوير خوارزميات للسماح للناس بإمتلاك ماكينات، مثل أجهزة واي فاي،
and overlay them with a sharing protocol that would allow a community like this
وتزويدها ببروتوكولات تقاسم التي ستتيح لمجتمع مثل هذا
to build its own wireless broadband network simply from the simple principle:
لبناء شبكته اللاسلكية الخاصة ذات النطاق العريض ببساطة عبر المبدأ البسيط:
When I'm listening, when I'm not using, I can help you transfer your messages;
بينما أسمع أنا، عندما لا أستخدم، يمكنني مساعدتك في نقل رسائلك.
and when you're not using, you'll help me transfer yours.
وعندما لا تستخدم أنت، ستساعدني في نقل رسائلي.
And this is not an idealized version. These are working models that at least in some
وهذا ليس النموذج المثالي. هذه نماذج عاملة على الأقل في بعض
places in the United States are being implemented, at least for public security.
الأماكن في الولايات المتحدة يتم تطبيقها، على الأقل لخدمة الأمن العام.
If in 1999 I told you, let's build a data storage and retrieval system.
إن أخبرتكم عام 1999، لنبني نظام تخزين وإسترجاع بيانات.
It's got to store terabytes. It's got to be available 24 hours a day,
ولديه مخزن بيانات تيرابايتات. وسيكون متوفراً ل 24 ساعة يومياً،
seven days a week. It's got to be available from anywhere in the world.
سبعة ايام أسبوعياً. ويجب أن يتوافر من أي مكان في العالم.
It has to support over 100 million users at any given moment. It's got to
ولديه دعم من 100 مليون مستخدم في كل لحظة. وهو آمن من
be robust to attack, including closing the main index, injecting malicious files,
الهجمات، وضمنها إغلاق الفهرس الرئيسي، وحقنه بملفات خبيثة،
armed seizure of some major nodes. You'd say that would take years.
مسلح ببعض النقاط الرئيسية. فأنك ستقول أنه سيستغرق سنوات.
It would take millions. But of course, what I'm describing is P2P file sharing.
ربما يكلف ملايين. لكن بالطبع، ما أقوم بوصفه هو نظام تقاسم الملفات P2P.
Right? We always think of it as stealing music, but fundamentally,
صحيح؟ نحن دائماً نفكر بها كسرقة للموسيقى، لكن في الأساس،
it's a distributed data storage and retrieval system, where people,
هو نظام تخزين وإسترجاع موزّع، حيث يرغب الناس،
for very obvious reasons, are willing to share their bandwidth and their
لأسباب واضحة للغاية، في تقاسم عرض نطاقهم الترددي و
storage to create something.
تخزينهم لصنع شئ.
So, essentially what we're seeing is the emergence of a fourth transactional
إذاً فان ما نشهده في الأساس هو ظهور الإطار الرابع
framework. It used to be that there were two primary dimensions along which
للمعاملات. كان من المعتاد أن هناك بُعدين أساسيين يمكنك
you could divide things. They could be market based, or non-market based;
بناء عليهما تقسيم الأشياء. قد تكون على أساس السوق، أو غير سوقية.
they could be decentralized, or centralized.
قد تكون لا مركزية، أو مركزية.
The price system was a market-based and decentralized system.
نظام الأسعار كان على الأساس السوق ونظام لا مركزي.
If things worked better because you actually had somebody organizing them,
إن سارت الأمور بصورة أفضل فأنك ستجلب شخص ما لإدارتها،
you had firms, if you wanted to be in the market -- or you had governments
كان لديك شركات إن أردت أن تصبح سوقاً -- أو لديك حكومات
or sometimes larger non-profits in the non-market.
أو بعض الأحيان منظمات لا ربحية أكبر في غير سوقية.
It was too expensive to have decentralized social production,
لقد كان الحصول على إنتاج إجتماعي لا مركزي مكلفاً للغاية،
to have decentralized action in society. That was not about society itself.
للحصول على فعل لا مركزي في المجتمع-- ذلك غير متعلق بالمجتمع نفسه.
That was, in fact, economic.
لقد كان في الواقع حول الإقتصاد.
But what we're seeing now is the emergence of this fourth system
لكن ما نشهده الآن هو ظهور هذا النظام الرابع
of social sharing and exchange.
للتقاسم المجتمعي والتبادل.
Not that it's the first time that we do nice things to each other, or for each other,
تلك ليست المرة الأولى التي نفعل فيها أشياء جيدة من أجل أو لبعضنا البعض،
as social beings. We do it all the time.
ككائنات إجتماعية. نحن نفعلها طوال الوقت.
It's that it's the first time that it's having major economic impact.
بل أنها لأول مرة يكون لديها تأثير إقتصادي رئيسي.
What characterizes them is decentralized authority.
ما يميزها هي لا مركزية السلطة.
You don't have to ask permission, as you do in a property-based system.
لا ينبغي عليك أن تطلب اذناً، لأنك تفعلها في نظام قائم على الملكية.
May I do this? It's open for anyone to create and innovate and share,
ربما أفعل هذا؟ إنه مفتوح لأي شخص أن يبدع ويبتكر ويتقاسم،
if they want to, by themselves or with others,
إن أرادوا ذلك، بأنفسهم أو مع آخرين،
because property is one mechanism of coordination.
لأن الملكية هي أحد آليات التنسيق.
But it's not the only one.
لكنها ليست الوحيدة.
Instead, what we see are social frameworks for all of the critical things that we use
بدلاً عن ذلك، ما نراه هو أطر إجتماعية لكل الأشياء الحرجة التي نستخدمها
property and contract in the market: information flows to decide what are
الملكية والعقد في السوق. تتدفق المعلومات لنقرر ما هي
interesting problems; who's available and good for something;
المشاكل المثيرة، من المتوفر وجيد لأداء شئ،
motivation structures -- remember, money isn't always the best motivator.
هياكل التحفيز -- تذكروا، المال ليس دائماً أفضل الحوافز.
If you leave a $50 check after dinner with friends,
إذا تركت شيكاً بعد العشاء مع أصدقائك،
you don't increase the probability of being invited back.
فأنك لا تزيد من إحتمال أن تتم دعوتك مجدداً.
And if dinner isn't entirely obvious, think of sex. (Laughter)
وإذا كان العشاء ليس من أجل هدف واضح، فكروا بالجنس. (ضحك)
It also requires certain new organizational approaches.
إنه يتطلب مقاربة مؤسسية محددة وحديثة.
And in particular, what we've seen is task organization.
وبالتحديد، ما رأيتموه هو مهمة مؤسسة.
You have to hire people who know what they're doing.
ينبغي عليك توظيف أناس يعرفون ما يفعلون.
You have to hire them to spend a lot of time.
ينبغي عليك توظيفهم لقضاء الكثير من الوقت.
Now, take the same problem,
الآن، لنأخذ نفس المشكلة،
chunk it into little modules, and motivations become trivial.
نقوم بتجزئتها لنماذج أصغر، وتصبح الحوافز تافهة.
Five minutes, instead of watching TV?
خمس دقائق، بدلاً عن مشاهدة التلفاز؟
Five minutes I'll spend just because it's interesting. Just because it's fun.
خمس دقائق سأقضيها فقط لأنها ممتعة. فقط لأنها مرحة.
Just because it gives me a certain sense of meaning, or, in places that are more
فقط لأنها تعطيني إحساس محدد بالمعنى، أو، في أماكن أكثر
involved, like Wikipedia, gives me a certain set of social relations.
ضلوعاً، مثل ويكي بيديا، تعطيني مجموعة محددة من العلاقات الإجتماعية.
So, a new social phenomenon is emerging.
إذاً فهي ظاهرة إجتماعية جديدة بدأت في الظهور.
It's creating, and it's most visible when we see it as a new form of competition.
إنها صانعة، وهي الأكثر وضوحاً حينما نراها، كشكل جديد للمنافسة.
Peer-to-peer networks assaulting the recording industry;
شبكات الند للند تعتدي على قطاع التسجيلات.
free and open source software taking market share from Microsoft;
برمجيات المصدر المفتوح والمجانية تأخذ حصة سوقية من مايكروسوفت.
Skype potentially threatening traditional telecoms;
سكايب لديه قابلية تهديد الإتصالات التقليدية.
Wikipedia competing with online encyclopedias.
ويكي بيديا تتنافس مع الموسوعات على الإنترنت.
But it's also a new source of opportunities for businesses.
لكنها أيضاً مصدر جديد للفرص بالنسبة للأعمال.
As you see a new set of social relations and behaviors emerging,
كما ترون مجموعة جديدة من العلاقات الإجتماعية والسلوك يظهر،
you have new opportunities. Some of them are toolmakers.
فان لديكم فرصاً جديدة. بعضها هي صانعي الأدوات.
Instead of building well-behaved appliances
بدلاً عن بناء أجهزة تُحسن التصرف
-- things that you know what they'll do in advance --
-- أشياء تعرف أنها ستؤدي مقدماً --
you begin to build more open tools. There's a new set of values,
فأنك تبدأ ببناء أدوات مفتوحة أكثر. هناك مجموعة قيّم جديدة،
a new set of things people value.
مجموعة جديدة من الأشياء التي يقدرها الناس.
You build platforms for self-expression and collaboration.
أنت تبني أطر للتعبير عن الذات والتعاون.
Like Wikipedia, like the Open Directory Project,
مثل ويكي بيديا، مثل مشروع الفهرس المفتوح،
you're beginning to build platforms, and you see that as a model.
أنت تقوم ببناء أطر، وترونه كنموذج.
And you see surfers, people who see this happening, and in some sense
وترى المستخدمين، الناس الذين يرون هذا يحدث، وبطريقة ما
build it into a supply chain, which is a very curious one. Right?
تتحول إلى سلسلة توريد، التي هي غريبة للغاية. صحيح؟
You have a belief: stuff will flow out of connected human beings.
لديك إيمان: ستتدفق الأشياء إلى البشر الموصولين.
That'll give me something I can use, and I'm going to contract with someone.
الشئ الذي سيعطيني شئ يمكنني إستخدامه، وسأقوم بالتعاقد مع شخص ما.
I will deliver something based on what happens. It's very scary
سأقوم بارسال شئ بناء على ما سيحدث. إنه مخيف للغاية
-- that's what Google does, essentially.
-- ذلك ما تفعله غوغل، في الأساس.
That's what IBM does in software services, and they've done reasonably well.
ذك ما تفعله IBM في خدمات البرمجيات، ولقد أبلوا بلاء حسناً.
So, social production is a real fact, not a fad.
إذاً، فالإنتاج الإجتماعي هو حقيقة ماثلة، ليس بدعة.
It is the critical long-term shift caused by the Internet.
إنه تحول حرج على المدى الطويل سببته الإنترنت.
Social relations and exchange become significantly more important than they ever
العلاقات الإجتماعية والتبادل تصبح أكثر أهمية بكثير عن أي وقت مضى
were as an economic phenomenon. In some contexts, it's even more efficient
كظاهرة إقتصادية. في بعض السياقات، إنها أكثر كفاءةً
because of the quality of the information, the ability to find the best person,
بسبب جودة المعلومات، المقدرة على إيجاد أفضل شخص،
the lower transaction costs. It's sustainable and growing fast.
أقل تكاليف للعملية. إنها مستدامة وتتنامى بسرعة.
But -- and this is the dark lining -- it is threatened by
لكن -- وهذا هو الجانب المظلم -- إنها مهددة من قبل
-- in the same way that it threatens -- the incumbent industrial systems.
-- بنفس الطريقة التي تهدد بها -- الأنظمة الصناعية الحالية.
So next time you open the paper, and you see an intellectual property decision,
لذا ففي المرة القادمة التي تقرأ فيها ورقة، وترى قرار عن الملكية الفكرية،
a telecoms decision, it's not about something small and technical.
أو قرار عن الإتصالات، فانه ليس حول شئ صغير وتقني.
It is about the future of the freedom to be as social beings with each other,
إنه حول مستقبل الحرية لنكون كائنات إجتماعية مع بعضنا البعض،
and the way information, knowledge and culture will be produced.
والطريقة التي عبرها تُنتج المعلومات، المعرفة والثقافة.
Because it is in this context that we see a battle over how easy or hard it will be
لأنها في هذا السياق الذي نرى فيه معركة حول كم هو سهل أم صعب
for the industrial information economy to simply go on as it goes,
بالنسبة لإقتصاد المعلومات الصناعي ليتواصل كما هو حاله،
or for the new model of production to begin to develop alongside that industrial model,
أو للنموذج الحديث للإنتاج لنبدأ بتطويره بجانب ذلك النموذج الصناعي،
and change the way we begin to see the world and report what it is that we see.
ونغيّر الطريقة التي نرى بها العالم ونبلغ عن ما نراه.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.